<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<feed xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<title>Robin (axcelott)</title>
<subtitle>Thoughts and opinions of a teenager from the Netherlands.</subtitle>
<id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/</id>
<link href='https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/' />
<author>
<name>Robin Boers</name>
<email>webmaster@roblog.nl</email>
</author>
<rights>Copying is an act of love. Please copy.</rights>
<updated>2024-05-31T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
<link href='https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/atom.xml' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml' />
<entry>
  <title>The Next Stage of the Web Browser</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/dream-browser" />
  <published>2024-05-31T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-06-13T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/dream-browser</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  In his post  <a href="//bandukwala.me/on-compositional-window-management/">   <cite>    On compositional window management   </cite>  </a>  Alexander Bandukwala explores ways in which window managers could be          improved. I can’t help but draw parallels to modern web          browsers. Applications reimplement the window managers due to the          limited feature set. Websites reimplement the web browser in the same          way. </p> <p>  <a href="/v/19/blog/web-sdk">   I complained  </a>  in the past, that I want the          browser to be  <em>   just a document reader  </em>  . But let’s face          it; it’s not. It’s really just an SDK. But even for an          SDK, it’s pretty bad. </p> <p>  Websites keep reimplementing the browser using JS, because the browser  <em>   sucks  </em>  . Despite all their fancy advertising and redesigns,          browser haven’t really evolved for the last decade. Yea,          they’ve implemented a bunch more ridiculous Javascript APIs, but          what real added value do they provide to the end-user? </p> <p>  Here’s some things I’d want in my browser: </p> <ul>  <li>   <p>    You know all those cookie popups everywhere? What if they were              just part of the browser? Currently, every website is allowed to              save cookies by default. There’s nothing preventing a              website from saving cookies anyway when you tap the tiny              “no” button. What if we reverse that? Whenever a              website tries to save cookies, the browser displays a standard              popup with a clear “no” button that actually    <em>     denies the cookies    </em>    .   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    You know how websites have those complicated menus? Yea, what if              my browser just scraped their    <code>     sitemap.xml    </code>    and              compiled a convient index of the site for me?   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    And while we’re at it, why not render a table of contents              for every page? You know, those things Wikipedia and numerous              other sites are now inserting into their HTML, because our              document readers—oh sorry, I meant universal              SDKs—still don’t have this feature?   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    You know how links you’ve already visited turn purple              (unless the website overrides it). What if we would indicate the              target location of the link in a similar way? Links to other pages              on the same site would stay as-is, but outgoing links would get              some kind of extra indication. Also, it would be nice to know the              page size of the target page upfront, especially on metered              connections.   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    Also    <a href="/v/19/blog/hotfox">     bringing back RSS discovery and subscriptions    </a>    <em>     properly    </em>    would be pretty nice!   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    Having publishing built into the browser would truly democratize              the Web. Instead of the convoluted form-based UIs we could have a              simple HTML editor builtin that could publish using    <a href="//developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Methods/PUT">     HTTP PUT    </a>    if the target server supports it.   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    Imagine if supporting writers and other creative people was              built-in to the Web? A browser-native button to send the author of              the page/media element a few bucks would allow creators to              passively earn money by creating cool stuff. Maybe we could put    <a href="//developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Status/402">     HTTP 402    </a>    <i>     Payment Required    </i>    to good use?   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    And finally, how about actually useful building blocks for              applications, instead of this JS+form madness we have now? The              idea of building up the interface using a markup language such as              HTML or XML is very good, but what if we could also utilize              OS-native components in our designs?   </p>  </li> </ul> <p>  Could somebody at Google or Mozilla maybe pretty please make (some of)          this reality? /hj </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/dream-browser">    <time datetime="2024-05-31">     May 31, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Surf, don’t search</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/surf-dont-search" />
  <published>2024-05-29T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-06-08T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/surf-dont-search</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  You’re using the internet wrong. That’s quite a statement,          isn’t it? </p> <!--        &lt;p&gt;          A few months ago, I introduced my sister to &lt;a href=&#34;/rss&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;.          She seemed to like the idea, but she kept asking one question, over          and over. &#34;How do I find things to follow?&#34;        &lt;/p&gt;        &lt;p&gt;          Excellent question! How &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; you find interesting things on the          Web? The anwser? Browse it; follow links; surf around.        &lt;/p&gt;        --> <p>  The power of the Web is its hyperlinked nature. It’s a  <em>   web  </em>  , not just a repository. Yet we’re increasingly  <em>   searching  </em>  for everything on monolithic search engines like          Google. That’s bad. For one, it limits you to a very small          portion of the Web—and it’s not  <a href="/v/19/blog/love-hate">   the best part either  </a>  . </p> <p>  But also: our brain works by association: </p> <blockquote cite="https://thesephist.com/posts/nav/">  <p>   When I get stuck on a really hard problem, whether it’s some            impossible bug in my code or my sofa not fitting through my front            door on moving day, I close my eyes and … think really hard.            Somewhere behind my shut eyelids and confused eyeballs, things are            happening. Electricity is flowing through the vat of brain-stuff and            spindly wires that somehow make up my thought process, and for a few            seconds, they just kind of do their thing. Until, if I’m            lucky, an answer pops into my head a few moments later.  </p>  <p>   One of my favorite questions to ponder these days has been: when            I’m thinking or remembering, just in that moment when my eyes            are closed and I’m sending all that extra energy to my brain,            what’s really happening? There are no hard drives to spin into            place in my brain. What’s taking up all that time? It’s            easy to wave your hands and say “it’s just computing” or            whatever, the way you expect slow computers under load to be. But            often when I’m heads-down thinking, I’m not crunching            numbers or solving logic puzzles in my head. I’m not really            sure what I’m doing, but it usually feels like just staring            into the void and hoping for some idea to pop into my mind.  </p>  <blockquote cite="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1945/07/as-we-may-think/303881/">   <p>    The human mind […] operates by association. With one item in              its grasp, it snaps instantly to the next that is suggested by the              association of thoughts, in accordance with some intricate web of              trails carried by the cells of the brain. It has other              characteristics, of course; trails that are not frequently              followed are prone to fade, items are not fully permanent, memory              is transitory. Yet the speed of action, the intricacy of trails,              the detail of mental pictures, is awe-inspiring beyond all else in              nature.   </p>  </blockquote>  <p>   If we imagine the repository of ideas and memories in a mind as a            kind of tangled web of ideas, “thinking” definitely involves            traversing and scrambling across this web somehow, with some intent.            The more obvious, trivial thoughts are the associations that are            immediate and close by, and the more insightful thoughts may be            jumps between ideas that are only loosely connected, or only            connected by second- or third-degree leaps in association.  </p> </blockquote> <p>  The most valuable aspect of the Web is the ability to travese sources          in this way. By using a search bar you’re missing this crucial          aspect of the Web. </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/surf-dont-search">    <time datetime="2024-05-29">     May 29, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>The Web is the everything protocol</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/web-sdk" />
  <published>2024-05-27T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-06-08T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/web-sdk</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  I love building websites; I also  <a href="/v/19/blog/love-hate">   hate the Web  </a>  . </p> <p>  I like the concept of the Web: interlinked documents with optional          embedded media. Just pages of text with images and videos here and          there. Think books but with interactive elements. The Web was meant to          be that: a great document reader. </p> <p>  Yet we’re increasingly treating it as an SDK of some sort. A          Universal Application Development ToolKit. Further and further          emulating native applications using JavaScript APIs. </p> <p>  Just look at the ridiculous scope of these Javascript APIs:          WebBattery, WebBluetooth, WebGamepad, WebVibration, WebVR, WebMIDI,          WebUSB, WebDRM, and WebXR. What’s all this  <em>   stuff  </em>  needed          for? Yea, it makes sense for a Universal Application Development          ToolKit, but it’s absolutely absurd to implement in a document          reader: </p> <blockquote cite="//geminiprotocol.net/docs/faq.gmi#15-what-kind-of-timeless-user-experience">  <p>   [On gemini there’s] absolutely no question of accidentally            ending up [on] a shady [website] which starts using your computer to            mine cryptocurrency for somebody else, because what kind of insane            person would design document reading software where that’s a            thing that could possibly happen under any circumstances?  </p> </blockquote> <p>  The Web platform is so insanely overscoped, that it’s difficult          to even begin to understand: </p> <blockquote cite="//drewdevault.com/2020/03/18/Reckless-limitless-scope.html">  <p>   The total word count of the W3C specification catalogue is 114            million words at the time of writing. If you added the combined word            counts of the C11, C++17, UEFI, USB 3.2, and POSIX specifications,            all 8,754 published RFCs, and the combined word counts of everything            on Wikipedia’s list of longest novels, you would be 12 million            words short of the W3C specifications.  </p>  <p>   Web browsers are responsible for more than 8,000 CVEs.  </p> </blockquote> <p>  It’s easy to see why it played out like this. Nowadays, every          computer has a Web browser, which means a web app has perfect          cross-platform compatibility at virtually no cost. </p> <p>  Worse, the Web browser is becoming  <a href="//blog.cjeller.site/browser-as-os">   a standalone OS of its own  </a>  . Google’s literally made their browser their OS—and it          worked! To end users, the browser  <em>   is  </em>  the OS. It’s the          first thing they open when starting their computer. What little          “desktop” applications they install are often built with          Electron, which is just running a browser engine without the browser  <abbr title="Chrome is an alternative term for UI">   chrome  </abbr>  . </p> <p>  Yet again, it’s not remarkable that it played out like this: </p> <blockquote cite="//developers.slashdot.org/story/18/12/09/0941247/electron-and-the-decline-of-native-apps">  <p>   To paraphrase Churchill, Electron is the worst architecture for            desktop applications, except for all the other ones that have been            tried.  </p> </blockquote> <p>  My problem with the Web is that it’s trying to be two very          different things—and failing at both: </p> <ul>  <li>   <p>    An    <abbr title="Software Development Toolkit">     SDK    </abbr>    , a              platform for developing and shipping applications. Javascript is              an absolutely    <a href="//jsfuck.com">     horrible    </a>    <a href="//old.reddit.com/r/AskProgramming/comments/lwc3gj/why_a_lot_of_software_engineers_say_javascript_is/">     language    </a>    . For many advanced applications, the JS bundle is so              big—looking at you, Google Earth, that the poor Chromebooks              at school straight up crash; the only way to bring them back to              life is a hard reboot. Furthermore,    <a href="//kryogenix.org/code/browser/everyonehasjs.html">     not everyone can run Javascript    </a>    . So far for compatibility.   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    A good document reader—don’t tell me you think    <a href="/v/19/blog/love-hate">     this nightmare fuel    </a>    is decent.   </p>  </li> </ul> <p>  The Web tries to be everything. It’s a shopping centre, a          workplace, a cafe, a chatroom, a game engine. I just want it to be a          good document reader. </p> <p>  Building a single all-encompassing standard—an everything          protocol—was a mistake. </p> <p>  We have standalone protocols for those things, you know. We have FTP          and network shares for file sharing, IRC and XMPP for chatting, SMTP          and DMARC for email, and RSS for syndicating creative work to          audiences. </p> <p>  And if we don’t have protocols for the things the Web is          trying—and failing—to do, maybe, just maybe, we should          build them. </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/web-sdk">    <time datetime="2024-05-27">     May 27, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>The RSS Club</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/rss-club" />
  <published>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-06-08T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/rss-club</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  I’m setting up RSS-only posts on my site, inspired by Dave          Rupert’s  <a href="//daverupert.com/rss-club/">   RSS Club  </a>  , a ‘secret          society’ consisting of individuals that publish some of their          posts exlusively using the ancient peer-to-peer syndication protocol          named  <a href="/v/19/rss">   RSS  </a>  . </p> <p>  If you’re reading this, you’ve probably found this post          via my RSS feed. Congratulations, you’re considered a regular          reader, and thus rewarded with extra postings now and then. </p> <p>  Of course, RSS-only postings can still be directly accessed if you          know the URL. But they’ll be unlisted on the index and in post          archives. Public, but somewhat hidden. An open secret, if you will. </p> <p>  As with any club, there are some rules: </p> <blockquote href="https://daverupert.com/rss-club/">  <ul>   <li>    1st rule of RSS Club is “Don’t Talk About RSS              Club”   </li>   <li>    2nd rule of RSS Club is “Don’t Share on Social              Media”   </li>   <li>    3rd rule of RSS Club is “Provide Value”   </li>  </ul>  <p>   Don’t talk about it. Let people find it. Make it worthwhile.  </p> </blockquote> <p>  RSS-only postings will generally consist of loose ideas, short updates          and more personal posts. Things that I’d like to share, but not          put “out there”. Lil’ easter eggs for RSS          enthousiasts. </p> <p>  Thanks for keeping RSS alive. You’re awesome. </p> <footer>  <p class="rss-only">   This is a RSS only post. Not a secret; just not noteworthy enough to            be listed on the index.  </p>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/rss-club">    <time datetime="2024-05-26">     May 26, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>love, hate</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/love-hate" />
  <published>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/love-hate</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  This lyric from Olivia O’Brien’s song  <cite>   hate u love u  </cite>  summarizes my relationship with the Web          almost perfectly: </p> <blockquote cite="https://open.spotify.com/track/6ATgDc6e4sPn84hvJsAmPt">  <p>   I hate you, I love you   <br>   I hate that I love you  </p>  <p>   Don’t want to, but I can’t put   <br>   nobody else above you  </p> </blockquote> <p>  Cause, as a developer, I lóve the Web. The web browser is a blank          canvas that can be used to build virtually anything. HTML, CSS,          Javascript—the languages used to build websites—are easy          to grasp but at the same time extremely powerful and versatile. There          are APIs for literally anything I’d want to build. And unlike          low-level languages such as C and Rust, a website doesn’t make          me to deal with a complicated toolchain; I don’t need to think          about complex cross-compilation, memory allocation, dynamic linkers or          glibc. I simply upload my HTML files to my server using  <code>   rsync  </code>  , and it automagically Just Works™. </p> <p>  However, as a consumer, I absolutely detest the Web. It feels like          it’s turned from a wild, collaborative, global creative space          into something akin to a shopping mall. It’s just  <a href="//how-i-experience-web-today.com">   straight up depressing  </a>  . </p> <p>  Everyone’s talking about  <em>   monetization  </em>  ,  <em>   growth hacking  </em>  ,  <em>   ad-revenue  </em>  . Everywhere I go,          I’m met with pages full of plausible sounding AI-generated          SEO-optimized nonsense. I get asked to accept these  <em>   delicious  </em>  cookies, to sign up for the newsletter, and to          create a (  <em>   free!!  </em>  ) account. Also:  <em>   this content is better in the app  </em>  ! And we’re  <em>   announcing our next-gen AI-powered blockchain startup, check it            out!  </em>  All while some completely unrelated video starts autoplaying in the          background. And that’s without even talking about the ads. </p> <p>  These websites are not built for you  <em>   to read  </em>  , they are          designed for  <em>   extracting value from your visit  </em>  . Desperately          trying to squeeze every last drop of data out of you, before you          inevitably close the tab. </p> <details>  <summary>   Note about monetization  </summary>  <p>   It’s not that I think creative people shouldn’t be            fairly compensated. Of course they should. But this isn’t            about them. This is about a cultural shift that turns the Web into a            business platform.  </p>  <p>   If you make something—art, music, film—and put it online            for others to see, but also request to be compensated for your work,            that’s totally fair. But what we’re seeing now is            companies hijacking the Web, replacing genuine people writing making            real things, with SEO-optimized clickbait meant to make money quick.  </p> </details> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/love-hate">    <time datetime="2024-05-26">     May 26, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Darlings</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/darlings" />
  <published>2024-05-25T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/darlings</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article> <p>  The saying goes “kill your darlings”. When I have trouble          fitting my writing into a cohesive whole, it’s often because          I’ve tangled up multiple concepts or ideas; essentially          trying—and failing—to create a coherent two out of two,          although related, separate concepts—leaving them both          underdeveloped. </p> <p>  In those moments the best solution is to split up my text, to provide          each idea the space and care it deserves. </p> <p>  So maybe don’t kill the poor things. Just  <em>   viciously  </em>  pull them apart. </p> <footer>  <p class="rss-only">   This is a RSS only post. Not a secret; just not noteworthy enough to            be listed on the index.  </p>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/darlings">    <time datetime="2024-05-25">     May 25, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Challenge accepted</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/challenge-accepted" />
  <published>2024-04-23T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-06-08T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/challenge-accepted</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  A while back, I read  <a href="//gilest.org/indie-easy.html">   <cite>    Let’s make the indie web easier   </cite>  </a>  , and it really resonated with me. </p> <blockquote cite="https://gilest.org/indie-easy.html">  <p>   OK, developers, I have a challenge for you.  </p>  <p>   I’ll assume that we’re all on board with the 2024 indie            web revival. We all want things to get weird again, right? Yeah.  </p>  <p>   And, I’ll assume we all agree that owning your own website is            a good thing, and we all want more people to do it.  </p>  <p>   But here’s the thing: we need more tools for it. We need            simpler tools for it. And we need to make installing and using them            trivially simple.  </p>  <p>   We need a whole galaxy of options.  </p>  <p>   So that next time we say to someone: “You should own your own            domain, and publish on your own website,” and they answer with            “How?”, we can give an answer that’s more than just: “Install            Wordpress.”  </p>  <p>   If we want the future web we’re all clamouring for, we need to            give people more options for self-hosted independence. If we            seriously, truly want the independent, non-enshittified personal web            to flourish, we need to make it easier for people to join in.  </p>  <p>   Why not build static website generators that people can just unzip,            upload to the shared hosting they’ve just paid for, and start            using via a browser?  </p> </blockquote> <p>  Challenge accepted! </p> <p>  I’m building a successor to  <a href="//micro.geheimesite.nl">   neopub  </a>  , my microblogging          platform. It’s still in early development, but things are going          great so far. It’s loosely based on the original source code of          neopub—which is why its repo is hosted under the neopub          namespace—, but has been rewritten from the ground up. </p> <p>  Here’s the idea: </p> <p>  A single-person microblogging platform written in PHP8, built on open          standards. It supports  <a href="//microformats.org">   microformats2  </a>  ,  <a href="//w3.org/TR/micropub">   micropub  </a>  ,  <a href="//w3.org/TR/webmention/">   Webmention  </a>  , pingback, various          feeds,  <a href="//w3.org/TR/activitypub/">   ActivityPub  </a>  and  <a href="//openheart.fyi">   OpenHeart  </a>  , along with  <a href="//personal-web.org">   @mentions  </a>  , which I  <a href="/v/19/blog/mentions">   recently implemented on this site  </a>  as          well. There’s going to be a very basic web interface for writing          posts and uploading images. Additionally, there will also be a          CLI—I’m gonna be using it myself, after all. </p> <p>  To circle back to @giles’s post, I’m designing this thing          to ✨ just work ✨, Out Of The Box™. Because  <a href="/v/19/blog/defaults">   defaults matter  </a>  . People aren’t          going to bother figuring out how to setup some obscure plugin to          enable some weird protocol they’ve never heard of—but they          might just like it when their site automagically federates with          various social media platforms and pulls in comments from each one. </p> <p>  And to reemphasize his point:  <em>   installing this thing should be trivially simple  </em>  . It should          be as simple as creating an account on Bluesky. Cause if it’s          not, what’s stopping people from just switching to another          content silo?  <small>   (I’m using the   <a href="/v/19/blog/stupid-terminology">    c-word   </a>   on purpose. These            corporations don’t care what you post, as long as they can            make money off of it.)  </small> </p> <p>  Since the platform is written in PHP, it should work on virtually all          shared hosting, provided they have an up-to-date PHP installation.          Installing should be as simple as drag and dropping some PHP files          over FPT. To reduce friction even more, I’m using JSON files          instead of an SQL database, as setting up and connecting an SQL          database is often a mayor roadblock in installing a CMS, for a casual          person. </p> <p>  I’m also thinking about creating some sort of hosted application          that integrates with a bunch of common registrars, which would guide          newcomers through getting a domain name, picking a hosting plan and          uploading said PHP files. Pick a domain name, pick a registrar, pick a          plan, and have the service handle the rest for you. </p> <p>  Anyhow. </p> <p>  So far, I’ve implemented Webmention (both sending and          receiving), micropub (with a media endpoint), pingback (using  <a href="//webmention.io">   Webmention.io  </a>  to forward pingbacks as          webmentions), and RSS, Atom, JSON feeds. However, I’m still          trying to figure out how the actual fuck ActivityPub works, and the          frontend is nowhere near finished. </p> <p>  <a href="//git.dupunkto.org/neopub/untitled">   Here’s the prototype, if you’re curious  </a>  . It doesn’t have a name yet, tho. Any suggestions? </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/challenge-accepted">    <time datetime="2024-04-23">     Apr 23, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>@mentions</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/mentions" />
  <published>2024-04-09T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/mentions</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article> <p>  I’ve implemented  <em>   @mentions  </em>  on my site, inspired by          @devastatia’s site. This allows me to tag fellow Webmasters when          I write something referring to their work, hopefully starting          interesting conversations. </p> <p>  <small>   <ins>    Update: I’ve added a short breakdown of how I’ve              implemented it in the    <a href="//github.com/RobinBoers/roblog.nl#readme">     README for the source code of this site.    </a>   </ins>  </small> </p> <footer>  <p class="rss-only">   This is a RSS only post. Not a secret; just not noteworthy enough to            be listed on the index.  </p>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/mentions">    <time datetime="2024-04-09">     Apr 09, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Predictive policing</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/predictive-policing" />
  <published>2024-03-30T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/predictive-policing</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  Last week we were reading an article about predictive policing at          school. These are my two cents. </p> <blockquote>  <p>   In an era of tight budgets, police departments accross the country            are being asked to do more with less. To address this problem,            law-enforcement agencies are increasingly turning to data and            analytics to improve their ability to fight crime without            substantial increase in operating cost. Known as predictive            policing, these technologies and techniques empower police officers            to take a more proactive approach to both preventing crime and            solving open cases.  </p>  <p>   [T]he trend toward evidence-based [predictive] policing should            ultimately enhance the relationship between communities and police            officers.   <strong>    That’s because data-driven decision making is a step away              from decisions based on biases that can result in unfair              discrimination.   </strong>  </p> </blockquote> <p>  Allow me to disagree. In computer science there’s a principle of  <a href="//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GIGO">   ‘garbage in, garbage out’  </a>  : </p> <blockquote cite="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GIGO">  <p>   GIGO is the concept that flawed, biased or poor quality            (“garbage”) information or input produces a similar            result or output.  </p> </blockquote> <p>  Your predictive policing algorithm may be objective, but the data          it’s being trained on almost certainly isn’t. So          you’ve actually made it worse: decisions made by such an          algorithm are as biased as decisions made by humans, but with the          illusion of objectivity. You haven’t eliminated bias;          you’ve now institutionalised it. </p> <details>  <summary>   Extras  </summary>  <blockquote>   <p>    The use of data, like the use of any tool, leaves openings for              misuse. There’s a big difference, for example, between              predicting where crime is most likely to occur and    <strong>     developing a list of potential future offenders without probable                cause,    </strong>    a practice that certainly raises serious ethical and legal              concerns.   </p>  </blockquote>  <p>   Just let me get this straight. You’re talking about creating a            list of suspects for   <em>    crimes not yet committed   </em>   . What            happened to the principle of ‘innocent until proven            guilty’?  </p>  <p>   While the article mentions   <em>    the possibility   </em>   of misuse of            data for less ethical causes like this, it unfortunately            doesn’t explain how it’s gonna   <em>    prevent   </em>   data            being used for these purposes ¯\_(ツ)\_/¯  </p> </details> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/predictive-policing">    <time datetime="2024-03-30">     Mar 30, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>0x10
c</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/0x10c" />
  <published>2024-03-29T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/0x10c</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  It has been a few years since I learned about  <a href="//yewtu.be/watch?v=O1aCbbeFN7E">   0x10   <sup>    c   </sup>  </a>  (pronounced “ten to the c”) in a documentary about Notch,          the creator of Minecraft. It’s the game he built after he          stepped down from his role as lead developer of          Minecraft—Minecraft’s unfinished sequel. </p> <p>  0x10  <sup>   c  </sup>  was supposed to be a space-themed sandbox game. It          takes place around 281,474,976,710,656 AD, which is (you guessed it)          0x10  <sup>   c  </sup>  in hexidecimal notation. The game’s backstory,          as told by Notch on the blog, was this: </p> <blockquote>  <p>   In a parallel universe where the space race never ended, space            travel was gaining popularity amongst corporations and rich            individuals.  </p>  <p>   In 1988, a brand new deep sleep cell was released, compatible with            all popular 16 bit computers. Unfortunately, it used big endian,            whereas the DCPU-16 specifications called for little endian. This            led to a severe bug in the included drivers, causing a requested            sleep of 0x0000 0000 0000 0001 years to last for 0x0001 0000 0000            0000 years.  </p>  <p>   It’s now the year 281 474 976 712 644 AD, and the first lost            people are starting to wake up to a universe on the brink of            extinction, with all remote galaxies forever lost to red shift, star            formation long since ended, and massive black holes dominating the            galaxy.  </p> </blockquote> <p>  Among other things, the game featured an emulated 16-bit computer          named DCPU-16 that players could use to interact with their spaceship          in various ways, and they could even extend the game with self-written          programs. </p> <p>  I think that’s such a neat idea: a programmable environment          inside of the game. I’ve been thinking about a game with a          similar in-game virtual machine. The game would be written  <em>   in  </em>  that very virtual machine, and exposed to the player, so          that the player can interact with and change the game as the please,          while they play. Full control over the mechanics and environment of          game with live feedback; it opens up so many possibilities for          interesting gameplay. </p> <p>  Think of it like  <a href="//sonic-pi.net">   Sonic Pi  </a>  , but instead of          composing live music, you adapt your surroundings and  <em>   the literal laws of physics  </em>  . Creating gameplay and solving          challenges by adapting the rules of the game. The game doesn’t          guide the player, but the player has full control over the game. </p> <p>  Unfortunately Notch abandoned 0x10  <sup>   c  </sup>  , he never finished or          released it. I don’t know if this is how it was supposed to          work. There’s very little known about the game—a lot of          rumors and a few videos is all we have left. But I can’t get          this idea out of my head.  <em>   One day I’ll make this game a reality.  </em> </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/0x10c">    <time datetime="2024-03-29">     Mar 29, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Rules</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/rules" />
  <published>2024-03-21T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/rules</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  <a href="https://blog.geheimesite.nl/notes/regels/">   In the past  </a>  I’ve written about what I called “two rules for any          well-functioning group”: </p> <blockquote>  <ul>   <li>    Everyone behaves   </li>   <li>    Everyone should have fun   </li>  </ul> </blockquote> <p>  However, I was probably wrong. Because while small groups of people          are pretty much self-organizing, as the group grows, some hierarchy is          needed. In a relatively small group—everyone knows          everyone—rules are generally unneeded, as people tend to behave          properly due to peer pressure and social dynamics. However, the          controlling effect of peer pressure breaks down in larger groups,          because people are relatively anonymous. Social dynamics alone are not          effective anymore, hence the need for formal rules. </p> <p>  So while you can get away with my two rules for a small group,          let’s say a classroom of around ~25 people, they will most          definitely cause complete anarchy and chaos when applied to the entire          school of around 700 students. </p> <p>  I was right about one thing tho: </p> <blockquote>  If there is no basis for the rule, the rule doesn’t work, or the          rule is unneeded, it should probably not be a rule. </blockquote> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/rules">    <time datetime="2024-03-21">     Mar 21, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>HotFox: RSS superpowers for Firefox</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/hotfox" />
  <published>2024-03-20T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/hotfox</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  A few weeks ago, I ran across an old article about XUL, a XML variant          developed by Mozilla for use in the Firefox interface. They killed it          a few years ago in favor of HTML, once again leaving behind their          tried-and-tested solutions in their ever-lasting chase to be as cool          and hot as Google and its Chromium project. So, to try it out anyway,          I installed  <a href="//palemoon.org">   Pale Moon  </a>  , a Firefox fork that has kept          the traditional XUL interface in its former glory. </p> <p>  Part of said traditional interface was a subscribe button that popped          up in the toolbar while visiting some sites. When clicked, it showed a          list of all web feeds that the site exposed. By selecting one of them,          or by simply visiting the feed URL, you got this fancy feed preview          with an option to subscribe to it with your favorite RSS reader. </p> <p>  Why exactly did “modern” browsers remove this? When I          visit an RSS feed in contemporary Firefox, I get this monstrosity: </p> <figure>  <img src="/v/19/images/blog/rss-plain.png" alt="A bunch of confusing XML. Ew, that looks disgusting.">  <figcaption>   A bunch of confusing XML. Ew, that looks disgusting.  </figcaption> </figure> <p>  Why doesn’t the browser give me the ability to subscribe to a          feed (anymore)?  <a href="//www.feed.style" target="_blank">   Why is it left for developers to figure out  </a>  , when it should obviously be the browser’s job? </p> <p>  In an attempt to right this wrong once and for all, I built HotFox, a          browser extension. It does two things: </p> <ul>  <li>   It adds a button to the toolbar that shows if a site exposes web            feeds.  </li>  <li>   It makes unstyled RSS feeds readable; turning the absolute mess from            before into a more pleasant preview:  </li> </ul> <figure>  <img src="/v/19/images/blog/rss-fancy.png" alt="A pretty rendered RSS feed with suybscribe button. Phew, that&#39;s better.">  <figcaption>   A pretty rendered RSS feed with suybscribe button. Phew,            that’s better.  </figcaption> </figure> <p>  It’s available in the Mozilla Add-ons store, if you’d like          to try it: </p> <p>  <a class="button" href="//addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/hotfox-for-rss/">   Download  </a> </p> <br> <details>  <summary>   FAQ  </summary>  <dl>   <dt>    Why the name?   </dt>   <dd>    Fire is hot; idk it just sounded cool. There’s not really a              reason.   </dd>   <dt>    Why build a new extension when    <a href="//addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/rsspreview/">     it    </a>    <a href="//addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/awesome-rss/">     already    </a>    <a href="//addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/want-my-rss/">     exists    </a>    ?   </dt>   <dd>    Because this seemed like a fun project to learn something about              developing browser extensions.   </dd>   <dt>    Will there be a Chrome version?   </dt>   <dd>    No. I don’t use Chrome myself;    <a href="//blog.geheimesite.nl/2021/12/google-chromium-en-een-monocultuur-op.html">     I don’t like Google’s attitude    </a>    .    <br>    But kudos to them—they    <a href="//www.ghacks.net/2022/08/22/google-chrome-is-getting-an-rss-feed-reader-on-desktop/">     got it built in.    </a>   </dd>   <dt>    Where can I get it?   </dt>   <dd>    On the    <a href="//addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/hotfox-for-rss/">     Mozilla Add-ons store    </a>    .   </dd>  </dl> </details> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/hotfox">    <time datetime="2024-03-20">     Mar 20, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>In favor of the small</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/sources" />
  <published>2024-03-18T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-07-13T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/sources</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  Since the internet went mainstream in the 90s, information has been          readily available for everyone. But can it be trusted? What makes a          reliable source? At school, we seem to get taught ‘the bigger          the better’. Big news sites are generally considered          trustworthy, while small and relatively unknown sites, like personal          blogs or forums, are off-limits. However, in my experience, small,          specialized blogs are typically better sources than those big news          outlets. </p> <p>  For one, random people online usually aren’t writing to please          an advertiser, publisher or particular audience—they’re          writing because they’re passionate about the subject. This makes          a huge difference, as there is no financial incentive, no money at          stake, no undisclosed incentives, no monetary gain. They don’t          need to clickbait their writing; there’s no reason to maximize          views. A blogger that isn’t financially dependent on their blog          has no goal to track you or sell ads. They don’t  <em>   need anything  </em>  from their readers. </p> <p>  Furthermore, articles on credible news sites are generally written by          journalists, which is good. They fact-check and remain objective and          neutral. But, a journalist will always be a generalist: they know a          little about a lot. Bloggers, on the other hand, can be specialists          and will often have a more in-depth understanding of the topic at          hand. In other words: specialized blogs are usually more accurate than          media coverage on the same subject. You’re probably  <a href="//rubenerd.com/erwin-knolls-law-of-media-accuracy/">   familiar with this too, if you’ve ever read some news item            about your own profession  </a>  : </p> <blockquote cite="https://rubenerd.com/erwin-knolls-law-of-media-accuracy/">  <p>   I’ve mentioned a few times how easy it is to pick apart            inaccuracies in media coverage on a topic you know about, and the            unease that sets in when you realise every topic likely has the same            issues.  </p> </blockquote> <p>  Moreover, bloggers don’t have any restrictions on their writing:          they can make their articles as long, technical, and detailed as they          please, not having to tailor them to a specific audience. Whereas a          journalist has to make their writing accessible to a larger audience,          exchanging valuable detail for readability. </p> <p>  On blogs and forums, I know that what I’m reading is the          authentic and personal experience of an actual person — not some          corporate marketing bullshit. I’m not alone in this btw;          there’s a reason people  <a href="//dkb.blog/p/google-search-is-dying">   keep appending “reddit” to the end of their searches  </a>  . Small blogs are written by  <em>   people  </em>  . I think that scares          institutions like schools, which were created in a world where only          other big institutions, like media companies and publishers, had the          ability to put stuff into the world. “Oh no, actual people are          now able to write and publish stuff on their own!” PANIC! </p> <p>  The advent of the internet caused a huge shift in the way we find and          consume information. And we love change—if we’re the one          doing it. But for the rest of us, change is a threat. A threat to what          is familiar. Familiar is nice. Familiar is comfortable. But that          doesn’t mean familiar is good. Yet our education system keeps          desperately clinging onto what it finds familiar. </p> <p>  But what if we instead embrace the internet and the voices it gives to          ordinary people? Maybe a more diverse and less formalised set of          sources will actually be an enrichment for class. Offer us new          perspectives we hadn’t thought of before. </p> <p>  So, I think we should be more kind towards stuff written by people.          It’s not scary; it’s just different. </p> <details>  <summary>   Clarification  </summary>  <p>   The blogs I talk about here are not the commercial BuzzFeed kind of            blogs, but rather the things you’d find on the   <a href="//indieweb.org">    IndieWeb   </a>   or   <a href="//neustadt.fr/essays/the-small-web/">    Small   </a>   <a href="//www.marginalia.nu/marginalia-search/about/">    Web   </a>   .  </p> </details> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/sources">    <time datetime="2024-03-18">     Mar 18, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Good Defaults</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/defaults" />
  <published>2024-03-15T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-06-08T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/defaults</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  Most documents are written in Calibri or Arial, everyone uses Google,          and links on the second page of Google are rarely seen.  <a href="//archive.uie.com/brainsparks/2011/09/14/do-users-change-their-settings/">   Only 5% of users actually change the settings  </a>  . </p> <p>  This is the  <a href="//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Default_effect">   Default Effect  </a>  —people don’t change the defaults. Therefore, whatever          ships with your product, that’s what most users will use. But          why? </p> <p>  It comes down to  <a href="//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decision_fatigue">   decision fatigue  </a>  , a psychological phenomenon in which a person’s ability to          make decisions deteriorates after making many decisions. Constantly          making decisions is exhausting. Thus, when people are faced with          multiple choices, they tend to stick to the default ones. </p> <blockquote cite="https://bootcamp.uxdesign.cc/why-default-settings-matter-more-than-you-think-97af8c785edf">  <p>   People change the defaults if the effort required to change them            feels less than the annoyance of sticking with them.  </p> </blockquote> <!--Settings are complicated-and scary. The defaults work. Modifying them only poses the risk of breaking *something somewhere*, with no clue how to fix it.--> <p>  Furthermore, users assume us programmers to know better. And frankly,          we should. Just because we nerds like to play around with the settings          doesn’t mean everyone does. And it shouldn’t be necessary          either. Thus, the takeaway is: provide good defaults. </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/defaults">    <time datetime="2024-03-15">     Mar 15, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Introducing {du}punkto</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/dupunkto" />
  <published>2024-02-18T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/dupunkto</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  Last year, I posted  <a href="//classic.geheimesite.nl/v/18/thinking-about-tilde">   my thoughts on running a tilde/pubnix  </a>  . In a nutshell, I wanted to experiment with setting up a small          tilde, to learn more about Linux and the internet. And after a few          months of experimenting, I finally have a system that I’m happy          with. So today I’m introducing  <a href="//dupunkto.org">   {du}punkto  </a>  , my attempt at building  <em>   something  </em>  . </p> <p>  In short, {du}punkto is a small group of like-minded people who are          sharing a VPS. Everyone has access to the server over SSH or Mosh          (handy for areas with wonky connections). The goal is to learn new          things about *NIX systems, collaborate on code, experiment, and, above          all, have fun. I’m co-maintaining it with  <a href="//dupunkto.org/~msb">   MSB  </a>  , one of my best friends. The          website isn’t finished yet, but it has a little more info, if          you’re curious. </p> <p>  Our server is named  <code>   du11  </code>  , after my web server  <code>   s11  </code>  , and it’s running FreeBSD 13. I opted for BSD          because I like the tidy and organized folder structure, large repos,          and jails functionality. It’s running a bunch of services for          developing and collaborating on software. Most notably: </p> <ul>  <li>   Web hosting for every Unix user via a   <code>    public_html   </code>   folder in their home directory.  </li>  <li>   A Gitolite server with a cgit web frontend and mirroring to GitHub            and Codeberg.  </li>  <li>   FTP storage with a web portal.  </li> </ul> <p>  It’s also possible to run complimentary services in FreeBSD          jails, like: </p> <ul>  <li>   A CardDAV and CalDAV server for me and my girlfriend.  </li>  <li>   A Miniflux instance for personal use.  </li> </ul> <p>  I’m very excited about it. I’m looking forward to seeing          what we’re gonna do with it further. </p> <details>  <summary>   Future plans  </summary>  <ul>   <li>    A handwritten classic Minecraft server.   </li>   <li>    Gopher and Gemini hosting, using    <code>     public_gem    </code>    and    <code>     public_gopher    </code>    respectively.   </li>   <li>    A VSCode server, similar to    <a href="//vscode.dev">     vscode.dev    </a>    .   </li>   <li>    A Matrix homeserver with Whatsapp bridging.   </li>   <li>    A Mastodon or Lemmy instance?   </li>  </ul> </details> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/dupunkto">    <time datetime="2024-02-18">     Feb 18, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Movies and Limited Series</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/good-movies" />
  <published>2024-02-07T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/good-movies</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  So lately I’ve been watching a lot of Netflix. </p> <p>  Generally, I’m not the kind of person that consumes a lot of          media. I’d rather make things; I find creating things way more          satisfying. </p> <p>  However, I got a bit burned out in terms of ideas—I didn’t          know what to build— energy, and time (school am I right ✨). So,          instead I spent about 20 hours of my life staring at a screen, looking          at fictional characters living their almost perfect made-up lives. </p> <p>  Anyways, I really enjoyed these in particular: </p> <ul>  <li>   After  </li>  <li>   Tick, tick… BOOM!  </li>  <li>   Heartstopper  </li>  <li>   Inventing Anna  </li>  <li>   Bohemian Rhapsody  </li>  <li>   Love, Rosie  </li>  <li>   Friends with Benefits  </li>  <li>   Lady Chatterley’s Lover  </li>  <li>   The Girl Nextdoor  </li>  <li>   Queen’s Gambit  </li>  <li>   Don’t Look Up  </li>  <li>   Dirty Lines  </li>  <li>   The Social Network  </li>  <li>   The Playlist  </li>  <li>   The Social Dilemma  </li>  <li>   Yesterday  </li>  <li>   I Used to Be Famous  </li>  <li>   We Are the Wave  </li> </ul> <p>  I really enjoyed the miniseries in particular; it allows the filmmaker          to tell a more detailed story, yet it doesn’t require as much          time (and commitment) to watch, as opposed to, for example, a          7-season-long show. </p> <p>  A movie feels short when you’re used to a series. But          that’s part of the appeal I think. A movie doesn’t try to          suck you in, like a series does. It just tells a story. </p> <details>  <summary>   Context  </summary>  <p>   I wrote this a while back (somewhere fall last year), but I forgot            to publish it. I found the draft yesterday.  </p>  <p>   Also, a lot of movies listed above share one common theme:            they’re all semi-related to the reproductive system; I’m            a teenager, after all ;)  </p> </details> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/good-movies">    <time datetime="2024-02-07">     Feb 07, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>The role of generative AI in writing</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/gpt" />
  <published>2024-01-23T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/gpt</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  Since its introduction a little more than a year ago, we’ve been          discussing ChatGPT a lot at school. It’s an interesting topic,          for sure. How can it be used in school? By students or teachers? Is          using AI cheating? Will it interfere with the development of writing          skills or help? Should it be used at all? </p> <p>  Generally, we seem to have the urge to ban upcoming technologies that          radically change things. Indeed, I’ve repeatedly heard people          call to ban use of generative AI, calling it plagiarism and fraud.          However, like everything, the matter is more nuanced than seems to be          the case at first sight. Even if we were to completely ban generative          AI, enforcing a ban like that will prove harder and harder the further          models like GPT evolve. Besides, it probably won’t restrain          students from using models like them. Therefore, we should think about          and discuss how we could properly integrate AI models into our          writing. </p> <p>  With that in mind, here are some of the primary takeaways after using          ChatGPT on-and-off for about a year. </p> <p>  ChatGPT is—mistakenly—mainly used to  <em>   generate  </em>  prose. However, the prose it generates is mediocre;          it’s dull and repetitive. Moreover,—even tho OpenAI tries          to prevent it—the model hallucinates fairly often. This means          nothing it generates can be trusted to be factually correct. </p> <p>  Instead, it is way more powerful as a tool to edit and transform          language. As Linus wrote a while back: </p> <blockquote cite="https://thesephist.com/posts/latent/">  <p>   Not “computers can complete text prompts, now what?” but            “computers can understand language, now what?”  </p> </blockquote> <p>  The AI models are unable to understand what they are writing about.          They’re only selecting words that sound plausible given the          context of their training data and the prompt. But they do know          grammar, spelling, and essay structure. That’s where their          strength lies. Not the ability to generate okay-sounding essays, but          their ability to understand and transform language. Use it to your          advantage. </p> <p>  Instead of prompting “can you generate an argumentative essay on          the role of religion in public schools”, we should prompt things          like “can you rewrite this paragraph to be more academic”          or “can you show me alternatives to this sentence”. </p> <p>  ChatGPT and similar models are not a threat to writing. Instead, they          are merely new tools that can—if utilized          correctly—further improve our writing. The impact they will have          is purely defined by how we use them. </p> <p>  <small>   *this post was written by me, but edited and   <a href="//languagetool.org">    checked for grammar mistakes   </a>   using            AI.  </small> </p> <details>  <summary>   Extras  </summary>  <p>   Some additional notes:  </p>  <ul>   <li>    LLMs are best used in combination with existing tools, like    <a href="//jsomers.net/blog/dictionary">     a good dictionary    </a>    ,              thesaurus, and spell checkers.   </li>   <li>    It’s really a bit silly to call this category of AI              “generative”, because (in my opinion) that’s the              thing they’re worst at.   </li>   <li>    While not really related to this topic, the    <a href="//thesephist.com/posts/latent/">     post I quoted from Linus    </a>    is great and you should definitely read it!   </li>  </ul> </details> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/gpt">    <time datetime="2024-01-23">     Jan 23, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Stop saying “users” and “content”</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/stupid-terminology" />
  <published>2024-01-15T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/stupid-terminology</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  Terminology like  <em>   users  </em>  and  <em>   content  </em>  is demeaning and          hurtful. </p> <p>  Artists aren’t creating  <em>   content  </em>  to populate our          datasets—they’re creating movies, music, essays, drawings,          games, paintings. Labeling a work that someone created, out of passion          and love,  <em>   content  </em>  , is frankly disrespectful. It reduces the          creative work from something beautiful to merely another piece of  <em>   content  </em>  , and greatly undervalues the effort and skill          necessary to create it. </p> <p>  Likewise, calling people  <em>   users  </em>  , dehumanizes them. It turns          them into a mere datapoint, or worse, an asset to be exploited. </p> <blockquote>  <p>   There are only two industries that call their customers            “users”:   <br>   illegal drugs and software.  </p>  —  <cite>   Edward Tufte  </cite> </blockquote> <p>  Terms like these shift focus away from the humans in the equation.          Language is the lense through which we see the world. Use it wisely. </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/stupid-terminology">    <time datetime="2024-01-15">     Jan 15, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Banning phones is not solving anything</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/symptom-relief" />
  <published>2024-01-14T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/symptom-relief</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  A few days ago, I posted some of my thoughts regarding the new mobile          phone ban in high schools in the Netherlands. I want to add a few more          things: </p> <p>  I think the fundamental problem is not the phones themselves. Why are          phones distracting? Push notifications and FOMO.  <em>   The phones are not the problem, social media is  </em>  . And because          we failed to properly regulate social media, phones are getting          banned. </p> <p>  The ban is a prime example of symptom relief. The government is doing          nothing to actually address the problem; all they’re doing is          prohibiting the manifestation. The ban will  <em>   not  </em>  help students          overcome their addiction. Neither is the ban preventing social media          use and all the problems than come with it; students are simply going          to use different devices to access their beloved Snapchat selfies. </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/symptom-relief">    <time datetime="2024-01-14">     Jan 14, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Thoughts on the mobile phone ban</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/phones-banned" />
  <published>2024-01-08T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/phones-banned</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  Last month the Dutch government announced that from next year on          mobile phones will be banned in high school. As a student who is          currently in high school, I think it’s a fundamentally good          development, but the media attention around it just feels wrong. </p> <p>  The news is full of items of cherry-picked comments from teenagers who          feel “relieved” because they “finally talk to each          other”. But also teenagers who are sad because “they          won’t have any memories of high school if they can’t take          photos”. They present a greatly exaggerated story praising this          measure the government imposed to protect the youth against          themselves. </p> <p>  It’s all so over the top. Contrary to popular belief, teenagers  <em>   do  </em>  talk to each other, even in the presence of a mobile          phone. In breaks, we play card games like Uno and Bullshit. We read          books. We complain about how stupid school and homework is. You know,          normal stuff. And our phones have a place too. Sometimes we play          mobile games in the break, like  <a href="//www.evilapples.com" target="_blank">   Evil Apples  </a>  or  <a href="//garticphone.com/" target="_blank">   Gartic Phone  </a>  . But          that’s still something we do  <em>   together  </em>  . </p> <p>  And, yes, phones are distracting. Yes, they cause mayhem from time to          time. Yes, social media is shit. I am very much aware. But all of that          is also true for adults. These devices and the apps on them are made          to be extremely addictive, it’s their fucking business model.          It’s not just teenagers who get addicted. And it’s          certainly not our fault that we get addicted. Even the people who          built these apps in the first place, who know exactly how they work          and what tricks are used to exploit our psychology, they still  <a href="//thesocialdilemma.com">   aren’t able to restrain themselves  </a>  . Adults aren’t magically immune. </p> <p>  It feels like it’s a bunch of grey birds going “kids these          days…”, “you can’t get off your phones, and          now we’re going to take them away”, “it’s for          your own good!” and then continuing to celebrate on social          media. Hypocrisy at its peak. </p> <p>  So yes, I think it’s great that phones have been banned in high          schools. The next step would be everywhere else (and especially the          parlement). </p> <details>  <summary>   Extras  </summary>  <p>   Some other notes:  </p>  <ul>   <li>    <p>     Schools spent years digitizing everything. Schedules, grades,                homework, study materials and more are now all exclusively                available in web applications. They made this move with the                assumption that these platforms would always be accessible for                students via their mobile phone (a wrong assumption by the way,                because this excludes students like myself that would rather                leave their phone at home). How are schools going to deal with                this?    </p>   </li>   <li>    <p>     How are schools going to enforce this? They’ve been                burdened with enough additional administrative tasks already.                And what even counts as a mobile phone?     <del>      Do all mobile devices count? What about my iPad? Or an old                  iPod Touch? My DIY Raspberry Pi Zero project with a                  rectangular touch screen? And what if it were a square                  instead? And what about smartwatches? They can TikTok too.                  Does every portable device with an internet connection fall                  under this new law?     </del>    </p>    <p>     <ins>      Update: I read the law on rijksoverheid.nl and they include                  “smartphones”, “tablets”, and                  “smartwatches”.      <em>       However      </em>      , they do not                  provide a definition for these terms. Disappointing.     </ins>    </p>   </li>  </ul> </details> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/phones-banned">    <time datetime="2024-01-08">     Jan 08, 2024    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Phones, assumptions and expectations</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/phones" />
  <published>2023-12-29T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/phones</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  I’m 16 years old. I strongly dislike my phone. You never thought          you’d ever hear those two sentences from the same person, did          you? </p> <p>  I started feeling like this a few years back. My parents decided I          couldn’t charge my phone at night, and consequently my phone          died a lot during the day. After a while, I stopped missing it. Even          if I have it with me, I don’t use it anymore.  <a href="//blog.geheimesite.nl/2022/03/een-maand-zonder-telefoon.html">   Last year, I challenged myself to put away my phone for a month  </a>  , and my primary conclusion was that most inconvience caused by not          having a phone, is imposed by the expectations and assumptions of          other people. </p> <p>  I hate the fact that I’m expected to always be available for          everyone. All it takes is one tap:  <i>   ping  </i>  . It’s annoying.          Every time I’m trying to actually get something done, my phone          just keeps going  <i>   beep boop ping pong  </i>  . It’s like someone          is tapping my shoulder every few minutes. “Can I have your          attention please?” My concentration is already severly          fractured. I don’t want to know that you’ve tagged me, I          don’t feel like sending selfies back and forth and I don’t          care that some artist released a new album.  <em>   I just want to get my shit done  </em>  . </p> <p>  Phones are supposed to be tools. Tools should never, ever,  <em>   ever  </em>  , have control over us. We’re supposed to be the          master of our tools, not the other way around. </p> <p>  That’s easily solved tho. My phone is always on silent. However,          people still  <em>   expect  </em>  me read and reply instantly. That’s          what bothers me: the fucking social pressure to participate. </p> <p>  Furthermore, everyone assumes you to have and always carry a phone          with you. Oh yes,  <em>   let’s do a Kahoot  </em>  ! Or some other activity requiring a          phone. Or  <em>   just scan this QR code and you’ll be done  </em>  . Or          how about we put the schedule on a mobile app? You’ll need a          smartphone to get a DigiD too, which is needed to access your medical          records, apply for vaccines, and pay your taxes. Sooner or later          you’ll need to setup mobile banking as well, because the device          we use for signing into the online banking portal doesn’t have          replaceable batteries and we won’t give you a replacement when          it eventually dies. </p> <p>  It’s the small things, the assumptions and expectations.  <br>  And it’s so annoying. </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/phones">    <time datetime="2023-12-29">     Dec 29, 2023    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>The Beginning</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/the-beginning" />
  <published>2023-11-09T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/the-beginning</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  The dawn of the universe is a paradox. There are two ways to explain          it: </p> <ul>  <li>   <p>    The universe has a beginning. Something initiated the universe,              which raises the question: how did that thing get there? And if              there was no thing—the universe sprung from              nothing—how can all be made from none?   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    The universe has no beginning—it has always existed in some              form or capacity. This seems contradictory: how can everything              exist forever? All this    <em>     stuff    </em>    must come from somewhere,              right?   </p>  </li> </ul> <p>  Saying you know the truth of the origin of the universe is lying to          yourself. Nobody knows — and nobody will ever know. We simply          can’t grasp the very beginning; it’s too contradictory.          It’s all-encompassing—too immense for a single human being          to fathom. </p> <p>  We must learn to live with the fact that we might never know the truth          to some things. And I know, that’s hard. It means letting go of          the little grip we have on reality. But ultimately, it’s the          only real answer we have.  <em>   We don’t know, and that’s okay.  </em> </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/the-beginning">    <time datetime="2023-11-09">     Nov 09, 2023    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/introduction" />
  <published>2023-10-15T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-05-26T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/introduction</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  Hi. So, you stumbled upon my blog, cool. </p> <p>  I’m a random teenager from the Netherlands, and this is my          little corner of the internet. </p> <p>  I post little notes about my life here. I made this site because I          love minimalism and the initial idea of the web: a giant library of          knowledge. This is my lil’ corner of that library—as          lightweight and simple as it can get. I’m not trying to scream;          I’m just looking to talk. </p> <p>  This blog is mostly for myself, but you can read along if you’re          inclined. I’m planning to do mostly long-form casual writing.          For now posts will be published exclusively on the Web, but I’m          looking into Gemini and Gopher hosting. </p> <p>  I’m really bad at these “welcome!!” kind of posts. Sowwy! </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/introduction">    <time datetime="2023-10-15">     Oct 15, 2023    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
<entry>
  <title>Waarom altijd meer?</title>
  <link href="https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/waarom-altijd-meer" />
  <published>2023-04-26T12:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2024-06-09T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://classic.geheimesite.nl/v/19/blog/waarom-altijd-meer</id>
  <content type="html">
    <![CDATA[
    <article>  <p>  Afgelopen jaar zat ik in de derde en moest ik mijn profielkeuze maken.          Op het vwo werkt het zo dat je tot de vierde klas  <em>   alle  </em>  vakken          krijgt, en daarna een profiel kiest met vakken waarin je examen gaat          doen. </p> <p>  Ik zit nu in 4 atheneum en het profiel dat ik heb gekozen is NT          (Natuur en Techniek). Dat betekent dat mijn vakkenpakket bestaat uit          natuurkunde, scheikunde, NLT, Duits, Nederlands, Engels, informatica          en wiskunde B. Volgens sommigen is dit het “moeilijkste”          pakket. </p> <p>  Kort samengevat is dit hoe er doorgaans tegen de profielen wordt          aangekeken: </p> <ul>  <li>   <p>    <strong>     <dfn>      Cultuur en Maatschappij     </dfn>    </strong>    : voor leerlingen die niet zo veel tijd aan school willen              besteden—met andere woorden: een pretpakket.   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    <strong>     <dfn>      Economie en Maatschappijl     </dfn>    </strong>    : voor leerlingen die niet het denkniveau hebben dat vereist is              voor de N-profielen, maar later toch    <em>     daadwerkelijk een baan zouden willen    </em>    .   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    <strong>     <dfn>      Natuur en Gezondheid     </dfn>    </strong>    : een soort “tussenpakket” voor leerlingen die een              nét iets te laag niveau hebben om wiskunde B te kunnen volgen,              waardoor NT geen optie is.   </p>  </li>  <li>   <p>    <strong>     <dfn>      Natuurk en Techniek     </dfn>    </strong>    : de alfa van de pakketten; voor de écht intelligente leerlingen.   </p>  </li> </ul> <p>  Enerzijds snap ik wel waar dit beeld vandaan komt. De exacte vakken          uit een N-profiel vereisen nou eenmaal een andere manier van denken          dan de zaakvakken uit een M-profiel. Maar dat maakt een NT-profiel          niet ineens meer waard dan de andere profielen. </p> <p>  Wel volgens mijn decaan. Vorig jaar kregen we van hem voorlichting          over onze profielkeuze, waarin hij kort uitlegde wat elk profiel          inhield. Hij benadrukte daarbij dat elk profiel gelijkwaardig is; een          diploma met een N-profiel is niet meer of minder waard dan een diploma          voor een M-profiel. Echter bleek vervolgens uit zijn hele verhaal dat          hij CM maar een pretpakket vond en het liefst ziet dat iedereen NT zou          doen. </p> <p>  Ik snap dat niet. Ik snap niet dat iedereen de hele tijd maar  <em>   meer  </em>  en  <em>   hoger  </em>  wil. Ik heb persoonlijk gekozen voor          NT omdat natuurkunde mijn favoriete vak is en kunst me helemaal niet          ligt. Niet omdat het schijnbaar het “beste” pakket voor de          “slimste” leerlingen is. Een aantal van mijn vrienden          hebben voor EM en CM gekozen, hoewel ik denk dat ze prima NG of NT aan          zouden kunnen; of ze daar blij van zouden worden is echter een ander          verhaal. Kortom, je zou het profiel moeten kiezen dat het best bij jou          en je interesses past, niet het “hoogste” dat je aankan. </p> <p>  En ik zie nu hetzelfde weer gebeuren bij de voorlichting over onze          studiekeuze. Want in principe leidt atheneum op tot  <em>   zowel  </em>  het  <abbr title="Hoger beroepsonderwijs">   HBO  </abbr>  als het  <abbr title="Wetenschappelijk onderwijs">   WO  </abbr>  . Maar in alle          voorlichting wordt het HBO gepresenteerd als “afstromen”,          of een “tussenstap op de ladder naar de universiteit”. </p> <p>  Maar wat als je nou helemaal geen ambitie hebt om naar de universiteit          te gaan? De universiteit is heel theoretisch. De focus ligt vooral op          leren onderzoeken, en je carriërepad na je afstuderen is vaak          onduidelijk, terwijl je op de hogeschool juist echt  <em>   een vak  </em>  leert. Persoonlijk zou ik liever naar het HBO gaan om          een docentenopleiding te volgen dan dat ik onderzoek zou gaan doen op          de universiteit, en ik ken een aantal klasgenoten die daar exact          hetzelfde in staan. De hogeschool is ook gewoon een          “eindpunt”, net als het wetenschappelijk onderwijs. Het is          niet een alleen een “tussenstap” of “plan B”. </p> <p>  Mijn zusje is nu ook aan haar profielkeuze toe. Net als ik zit zij op          het vwo (nu in de derde). Haar eerste keuze was NG op het vwo. CM ligt          haar ook wel, maar was geen optie omdat ze een hekel heeft aan          Duits—een verplicht vak in CM op vwo-niveau. </p> <p>  Onze school biedt ook een speciaal vak genaamd BSM (Bewegen, Sport en          Maatschappij) aan, waardoor je nu eindexamen kan doen in sport. Dit          past heel goed bij Lize, want ze is van plan circusartiest of          sportdocent te worden. Maar helaas is BSM uitsluitend te volgen op de          havo. </p> <p>  Daarom heeft ze besloten over te stappen naar de havo en daar CM te          doen met BSM als keuzevak. Ik denk dat dit een hele slimme zet is,          omdat ze iets gaat doen waar ze blij van wordt en dat goed bij haar          past. Maar in de ogen van onze geliefde decaan gaat ze van het          één-na-“hoogste” pakket op vwo naar het          “laagste” profiel een niveau lager: paniek! En hoewel ze          meerdere keren heeft aangegeven dat ze geen ambitie heeft naar de          universiteit te gaan en dat ze na haar eindexamen graag iets met sport          wil gaan doen, probeert hij haar toch krampachtig over te halen op het          vwo te blijven. Je wil toch het “hoogste” uit jezelf          halen? </p> <p>  Nu is mijn vraag: Waarom altijd meer? </p> <footer>  <p>   Posted on   <a href="//roblog.nl/blog/waarom-altijd-meer">    <time datetime="2023-04-26">     26 april 2023    </time>   </a>  </p>  <p class="reply-by-email">   <a href="mailto:replies@roblog.nl">    Reply by email   </a>  </p> </footer></article>
    ]]>
  </content>
</entry>
</feed>
